<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Count Mansfields directions of vvarre Giuen to all his officers and souldiers in generall.</title>
            <author>Mansfeld, Ernst, graf von, 1585-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06824</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17260</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120073</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855273</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855273</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20759</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06824)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20759)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 812:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Count Mansfields directions of vvarre Giuen to all his officers and souldiers in generall.</title>
                  <author>Mansfeld, Ernst, graf von, 1585-1626.</author>
                  <author>W. G., fl. 1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw: Allde for Richard Whittaker, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the Kings head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's dedication signed: W.G.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Military art and science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20759:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20759:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>COVNT.</hi> MANSFIELDS DIRECTIONS of VVARRE.</p>
            <p>GIVEN TO ALL HIS Officers and Souldiers in Generall.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>warrior figure with dog</figDesc>
               <p>♂</p>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Edw: Allde</hi> for <hi>Richard Whittaker,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, at the Kings head. 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20759:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20759:2"/>
            <head>TO The High, Mighty, and inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble CHARLES Prince of <hi>Wales:</hi> the Right Honourable GEORGE Duke of <hi>Buckingham:</hi> and IAMES Marqueſſe <hi>Hambleton;</hi> with the reſt of his Maieſties Honourable and faithfull Councell for Warre.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Sun is all one both to the Poore &amp; Rich: euen ſo (ſaith <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi>) ought a Prince not to haue reſpect to the perſon, but to the matter: Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon my ſelfe being not worthy, in reſpect of Prudence &amp; Experience, to ranke with the leaſt or meaneſt
<pb facs="tcp:20759:3"/>member of your Heroick Counſell, yet daring to compare with the Greateſt in my loyall meaning, fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and beſt wiſhes; reſpectiuely to his Maieſty, your Highneſſe, with reſtleſſe prayers for the proſperous proceeding of your true Noble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes; proſtrate at your Highneſſe feet, doe preſent theſe Directions for Warre, not to direct your Heauen-directed Counſels, but onely as a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pledge of my hearty deuotion, to acquaint you (for your better ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction) with the order of ſuch Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Diſcipline, as the Forraine Friends of Great <hi>Britaine</hi> in theſe tumultuous times doe exerciſe: their Motions, Standing, Marching, Fighting, Tyring and Retyring. In a word, the whole Art of Armes, taught and deliuered by this illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:20759:3"/>and renowned Figure of <hi>Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> (who firſt reuiſed and approued the ſame written) is heere exemplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; which I ſubmiſsiuely commend principally to the Patronage of your Princely Higneſſe, the moſt remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able object of Honour: beſeeching his Diuine Majeſtie, that like a moſt politicke and magnanimous Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, you may tranſcend not onely this Right-valorous <hi>Director,</hi> but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>Alexander Magnus</hi> in Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie Actions and Directions, and be <hi>Carolus</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Maximus:</hi> but much more Fortunate in Diuturnall fruition of your Conqueſts and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance: And that as you are the Glory of your Royall Fathers age, (according to <hi>Zeno's</hi> teſtimony) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing right Virtuous and Religious; ſo you may long ſuruiue and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
<pb facs="tcp:20759:4"/>the chiefe Columne and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of his Kingdomes; and no leſſe Defend the true Catholicke Faith: wherein the greateſt Guider of all Hearts direct mine, firmely to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and make mee euer ready and moſt willing (as at this preſent) to hazard my ſelfe and all that is mine in its Cauſe, as one that reſteth:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Moſt humbly Deuoted, To your Highneſſe: Your Graces: And the reſt Reſpectiuely Jn any Honourable Seruice <hi>W. G.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:20759:4"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <head>The Office of a Regiment and their Duties.</head>
               <item>THe Office of a Collonell. Page <hi>1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Office of a Lieutenant Collonell. pag. <hi>3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Office of a Sergeant Maior. pag. Idem.</item>
               <item>The Quarter Maſters Office. pag. <hi>4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Office of a Prouoſt of a Regiment. pag. <hi>5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Office of a Captaine of Foote pag. <hi>7.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Office of a Lieutenant of a Company. pag. <hi>10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Office of an Enſigne. pag. Idem.</item>
               <item>The Office of a Sergeant of a Company. pag. <hi>11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Office of a Corporall of a Company. pag. <hi>13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Office of a Lanſpreado. pag. <hi>17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Office of a Drum. pag. Idem.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The Office of a Troupe of Horſe.</head>
               <item>Captaine of Horſe. pag. <hi>19.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lieutenant of Horſe. pag. <hi>20.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Cornet. pag. <hi>24.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Quarter Maſter his Office. pag. <hi>26.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Trumpet. pag. <hi>27.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:20759:5"/>
               <item>Corporall of Horſe. pag. <hi>27.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The Dignitie of Souldiers in their Fyles.</head>
               <item>Of the Ordering of a Foot Companie, and of the Dignitie of each Souldier in their Fyle: with the manner of Exerciſing now vſed. pag. <hi>30.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Dignitie of Leaders. pag. <hi>33.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Diſtances. pag. <hi>37.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Generall Motions which the Companie or Troupes are to obſerue. pag. <hi>39.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Counter-March. pag. <hi>45.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Theſe following Motions are to be performed, both Standing and Marching. pag. <hi>50.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Motions Standing and Marching. pag. <hi>53.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20759:5"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE OFFICE OF A REGIMENT AND THEIR Duties.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Office of a Collonell.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very Colonell is to Command ouer all his Officers, Captaynes and others, and all Souldiers or men of Warre of what degree ſoeuer, that doth put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or are by ſuperiour Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie put and ranged vnder his Regiment: and all ſuch, as are to obey his commandement, and obey him as fully as they would doe the chiefeſt Commanders.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, hee ſhall ſee all Orders, Commandements, and Directions, which are deliuered him by the publike Officers of the Army, for Guards, Marches, Lodging, or any thing elſe; for matter of Iuſtice or for ordering the Troupes, and furtherance of the ſeruice duly executed or performed, within his owne Troupes.</p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:20759:6"/>
                  <p>Further if hee himſelfe doe finde any Mutinie, or diſcontented humours tending to mutinie, extreme out-rage, or diſorder; or ſhall by any of his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, Officers, or Souldiers, bee informed of any ſuch, hee ſhall forthwith aduertiſe the Generall thereof; And if he finde any other fault, negligence or ſwaruing, either from the Directions giuen, or the policy of the Army ſet downe, hee ſhall ſtraight way acquaint them, by whom ſuch directions did or was to come vnto him or ſome other ſuperiour Officer, if hee can conueniently acquaint him with it, and ſhall produce the partie ſo offending, with the witneſſes and proofes, that order may be giuen forthwith and Iuſtice done: and if he fayle to giue in this information of any thing he knowes or heares of, he ſhall be thought deeply faultie; or if any ſuch thing paſſe without his knowledge, hee ſhall be thought of worſe gouernment then were fit for a man of his place and charge.</p>
                  <p>Alſo in Lodging, euery Colonell is to lodge as neere as can bee in the middeſt of the Quarter aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for his Regiment, becauſe ſo he may giue dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for the whole.</p>
                  <p>In March, the Colonell ſhall be at the end of his Troupes that is neareſt the Enemies (that is to ſay) in the head of his Regiment, going towards an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, and in the Reere going from them; and he is not to ſtirre from thence vnleſſe it be for the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his Troupes or ſome extraordinary occaſion.</p>
                  <p>Alſo once euery weeke the Colonell ſhall call to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether all his Captaines, and ſhall enquire of all of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences in his Regiment, and examine the nature and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20759:6"/>qualitie of them to prepare the Cauſes, for a more ſhort and eaſie hearing in a Marſhall Court.</p>
                  <p>All Colonels ſhall repayre to a Martiall Court as often as they ſhall be warned, and ſhal be aſſiſtant to the Lord Marſhall in all cauſes that ſhall be there in queſtion, or belong to the Iuſtice of the Armie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Office of a Lieutenant Colonell.</head>
                  <p>THe Lieutenant Colonell, when his Colonell is preſent, is to aſſiſt and obey him, in ſeeing all directions performed that are deliuered by any publique Officer, or ſuch as ſhall be within the authoritie of a Colonell himſelfe to command; and in the abſence of his Colonell, hee ſhall haue the ſame authoritie the Colonell hath.</p>
                  <p>He is to lodge euer on the right hand of his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonels lodging, as neere the end of the Quarter as conueuiently may bee.</p>
                  <p>In Marching and Imbattelling, whenſoeuer his Colonell is in the head of his Regiment, he ſhall be in the reere of all that Regiment, and when his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell ſhall be in the reere hee ſhall be in the head.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Office of the Sergeant Maior.</head>
                  <p>IN the preſence of his Colonell or Lieutenant Colonell, hee ſhall be an aſſiſtant to them or ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them, in ſeeing all Orders and Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons executed and performed, and in the abſence of them both to haue the ſame authoritie, that the Colonell himſelfe ſhall haue.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:20759:7"/>
                  <p>He ſhall lodge on the left hand of his Colonell, as neere the end of his quarter as conueniently may be.</p>
                  <p>In Marching and Imbattelling, hee ſhall keepe as neere the middeſt of his Regiment as he can, but in the Flanke, and ſo as he may beſt ouer-looke the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his march or imbattelling.</p>
                  <p>He is to come to the Sergeant Major of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to receiue the Word from him, if there bee no extraordinary cauſe to hinder him: and when hee hath receiued the word from him, he is to deliuer it ouer to the Sergeants of the Regiment, and to all thoſe to whom it doth appertaine and to ſee them executed.</p>
                  <p>Euery Night he is to viſite all the Guards of that Regiment, and to keepe account of the turnes of the Watches, Marches, and ſending Troupes vpon ſeruice, to the end both the labour and the honour may be equally deuided.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Quarter Maſters Office.</head>
                  <p>IN all changes of lodging hee is to attend the Quarter Maſter generall, and to take the place by him aſſigned for the quartering of the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in ſuch forme as the Quarter Maſter generall ſhall direct him; and then he ſhall appoint lodging to the Colonels, and to the Officers, according to the places they are to take in the Regiment, and he ſhall not onely giue the height, the bredth, and the length of the Quarter to the furrier of euery Company, but alſo the diſtances from the Trench, if it be not an out Quarter, and the diſtance of one
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20759:7"/>Company from another, and when the Companies ſhall lye in Townes and Villages, hee is likewiſe to keepe proportion and follow the directions of the Quarter Maſter generall: he ſhall lodge the Sutlers of that Regiment, in the hindmoſt part of the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſuch a diſtance as the Quarter Maſter generall ſhall appoint.</p>
                  <p>His place is to lodge on the backſide of the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, behind the lodging of the Lieutenant Colonell.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Office of a Prouoſt of a Regiment.</head>
                  <p>HE ſhall ſee all Proclamations, Orders, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, that ſhall be publiſhed by the Prouoſt Marſhall of the Army, likewiſe publiſhed in the Regiment whereof he is Prouoſt.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, he ſhall ſafely keepe all Priſoners commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, and once a weeke to giue a note to the Prouoſt Marſhall of the Army, of all the Priſoners which is in his charge, and of the cauſes of their Commitments.</p>
                  <p>Further, he ſhall ouer-ſee all the Victualers of the Regiment, that they ſell not their Victuals either at vnteaſonable prices or vnlawfull houres, and ſhall on the other ſide be watchfull, that no wrong bee done vnto them; and if any bee, that forthwith the partie doing wrong be brought before ſome Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer that hath authoritie to yeeld redreſſe, and to that end he ſhall goe about the Quarter once euery fore-noone, and euery after-noon once, and once in the dead of the night, if it may be conueniently performed.</p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:20759:8"/>
                  <p>Alſo, he ſhall haue an Account giuen him euery night by the Victualers, what victuals are in the Quarters, and hee ſhall carry or ſend thoſe notes to the Prouoſt Marſhall of the Army.</p>
                  <p>When prizes or booties are brought in, after the Prouoſt Marſhall hath deuided the ſaid prey or bootie to euery Regiment, the Prouoſt of each Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment ſhall deuide them to the Companies.</p>
                  <p>It is his duty to ſee all the Quarter kept ſweet and cleane, all garbidge and filth buried, and to ſuffer nothing that may annoy the Quarter, within ſuch a diſtance as ſhall bee appointed him by the Prouoſt Marſhall of the Army.</p>
                  <p>Hee is to lodge in the middeſt of the Victualers of the Regiment.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall come to the Carriage Maſter for dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction where the baggage of that Regiment ſhall March, where they ſhall aſſemble, and what wayes they ſhall goe, which directions he ſhall ſee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: After hee bath giuen the firſt place to the Colonels baggage, hee ſhall marſhall the reſt by turnes, as the Companies ſhall march.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, he ſhall ſee the wayes made for the Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and the carriage accompanied with men ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and with Inſtruments to helpe or mend any thing that is amiſſe in the wayes, or carriages; or if any carriage ſhall be vnable to goe, he ſhall prouide that it be no ſtop or hinderance to the reſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:20759:8"/>
                  <head>The Office of a Captaine of foote.</head>
                  <p>HEE hath proportionably the ſame comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement ouer his Company, that a Colonell hath ouer his Regiment; and ſo all his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Souldiers are to obey him.</p>
                  <p>When hee receaueth his Company and his Armes, hee is to chooſe his men, and to ſort them to their Armes, as he ſhall thinke fit: prouided, that he make his ableſt men, armed men, and Muſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers: if he be to arme them himſelfe, he ſhall make the one halfe Pikes, the other halfe Muſquetiers.</p>
                  <p>Hee ſhall chooſe his Officers, ſuch as others haue had in the like place heretofore, and are of experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and good gouernment, or ſuch as haue made themſelues knowne to be fit for the like.</p>
                  <p>Hee ſhall deuide his Company into three Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral-ſhips.</p>
                  <p>Hee ſhall take care, and labour to teach all his Souldiers the carriage and vſe of their Armes, to keepe their orders in marching or imbatelling, to vnderſtand all manner of motions and ſounds of the Drumme; to this end he ſhall haue vſuall times of Exerciſing, which ſhall be once aday at the leaſt, till all his men be perfect.</p>
                  <p>In marching with his company alone, he ſhall be in the head of his company going towards an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and in the reere-ward, comming from an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</p>
                  <p>In Marching with a Regiment, he is to receiue his directions from the Sergeant Maior of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20759:9"/>Regiment, and to martiall his ſeuerall ſorts of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, as he ſhall be by him directed: and ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point to euery deuiſion of his Company, ſuch an Officer as the Sergeant Maior of the Regiment ſhall direct. And for the place, it ſhall be where the ſaid Sergeant Maior ſhall aſſigne him.</p>
                  <p>In imbatailing, hee is to order his Troupes as the Sergeant Maior of the Regiment ſhall direct, to be himſelfe where his Colonell or ſuperiour officer ſhall command him.</p>
                  <p>In lodging, he ſhall take his quarter aſſigned ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his degree and place in the Regiment, and ſhall ſee it built and ordered according to the directions his ſuperiours hath receiued; and that there be deuiſions, both of the quarter into ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons, and the ſquadrons into Comradoes or fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhips.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall haue his quarter kept ſweet for health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and quiet for order, eſpecially in the night.</p>
                  <p>If his whole company bee appointed to march, he ſhall draw out his company, and ſtand in Armes ready to march before his quarter, attending the directions of the Sergeant Maior of the Regiment. When he is brought to the place of his guard, he is to take directions of the Sergeant Maior of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, for placing of his <hi>Corps-de Guard,</hi> ſetting his Centinels, and ſending forth his Round, and to ſee the directions giuen him performed.</p>
                  <p>Hee is not to abandon his guard till he be relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and whatſoeuer is diſcouered, or brought to that <hi>Corp-de guard</hi> where he is, ſhall by him bee ſent to the Captaine of the Watch, and hee ſhall ſtill
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20759:9"/>make good his guard, if hee be not commanded by a ſuperior Officer to retyre.</p>
                  <p>If he heare of any muteny or diſcontented hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour tending to muteny, outrage, or any diſorder committed by any of his company within his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he ſhall forthwith aduertiſe his Colonell; or if hee be not in the way, ſome publike Officer of the Army and that he arreſt and bring forth the partie offending, with ſuch witneſſes and proofes as are to be produced, of which if he faile and know it, hee ſhall be held very faulty, and if ſuch things eſcape him, he ſhall be held vnworthy of his place.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall ſee on the other ſide, to thoſe of his Company that doe better then their fellowes, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced to place, and incouraged accordingly; and doe right to all of them, both in the pay and in all things elſe that are due vnto them, and ſhall as farre as in him lyeth, take care of the ſicke and hurt men.</p>
                  <p>In matter of ſeruice, he ſhall doe all that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him (by any ſuperiour officer that hath au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority) in the beſt ſort he can, without either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding his Commiſſion, or doing leſſe.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, when he is alone with his Company, hee ſhall be very vigilant and carefull, both in march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and lodging, and if he be put to any extremity, yet he muſt looke to make accompt, and therefore hee ſhall doe the vtmoſt, both by iudgement and valour to free his Troopes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:20759:10"/>
                  <head>The Office of the Leiftenant of a Company.</head>
                  <p>WHen the Company is preſent, he ſhall be an aſſiſtant to his Captaine in ſeeing all directions performed, that are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a ſuperiour Officer, all ſuch as his Captaine hath authority to command, and in the abſence of the Captaine, he ſhall haue the ſame authority the Captaine hath.</p>
                  <p>In Marching, if there bee no company but his owne, he ſhall be at the one end of his company, when the Captaine is at the other end: and if the company march with the Regiment, he ſhall take ſuch place, as the ſuperiour Officers that haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſhall aſſigne him.</p>
                  <p>In lodging, he ſhall be placed on the right hand of his Captaine, as neere the end of the quarter as conueniently may be, and ſhall in all ſeruices, and at all times helpe to keepe the Souldiers in Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and obedience, and ſhall performe all things commanded him, which are neceſſary to bee done by him, with valour and iudgement.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Office of an Enſigne.</head>
                  <p>WHen his Captaine or Leiftenant are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, he ſhall be aſſiſtant to them, or ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them, and in their abſence haue the ſame authority the Captaine hath.</p>
                  <p>In Marching, he is to catry his Enſigne, and take ſuch place as ſhall be aſſigned him: and if his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20759:10"/>be alone, hee ſhall either vpon entering his quarter, going out of his quarter, going vpon his guard, or vpon ſight of the Enemie, carry his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne aduanced and flying: and if he march with a Regiment, hee and all the other Enſignes of the Regiment ſhall doe as the Enſigne Colonell doth.</p>
                  <p>In Fight, he ſhall euer carry his Enſigne aduanced and flying, without offering to vſe it in any kinde of offence, being the ſigne for the Company to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by, and therefore to be preſerued: for which cauſe for his defence he is to vſe his Sword.</p>
                  <p>If he march with other Enſignes, he ſhall take ſuch place as ſhall be aſſigned him.</p>
                  <p>The Enſigne ſhall neuer turne his face out of his order, ſtart from any danger, nor forſake his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne vpon paine of death.</p>
                  <p>Whenſoeuer the Drumme ſhall beate for the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of the Company together, he ſhall be in the place, and ſhall ſee the Enſigne well guarded, and be ready to march, or doe any thing for the ſeruice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Office of the Sergiant of a Company.</head>
                  <p>IF all the three fore-named Officers be out of the way by any accident, then the eldeſt Sergiant is to command the Company as next in place.</p>
                  <p>In aſſembling the Company, he ſhall ſet euery man in his place, and if any be miſſing, hee ſhall ſeeke them out, and haue power to correct them: and if any be defectiue and not to be found, he is to acquaint his Captaine or Officer with it.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:20759:11"/>
                  <p>When the Company is aſſembled and ſet in order, he ſhall march in the out ſide, where he may beſt ſee the order of march obſerued: and to make the places of Sergiants more certaine, the eldeſt Sergiant ſhall march in the right Flancke, and take care from the Enſigne forward; and the youngeſt Sergiant on the left Flancke, and take care from the Enſigne backward.</p>
                  <p>Though he is to vnderſtand the vſe of all Armes vſually carryed, and all things elſe that belongs to a Souldier, yet he is eſpecially to make himſelfe able to direct and lead Shott, becauſe if his Company be alone and haue any fight, he is by cuſtome to conduct the Shott, in which caſe he is to follow the directions giuen him by his Captaine; or in his Captaines abſence, by any of his ſuperiour Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers.</p>
                  <p>And for his more perticular directions how to lead his Shotte after that he hath brought them vp to that ground, and in that number and order that his Captaine or ſuperiour Officer hath directed him, he ſhall haue euery man come vp cloſe to him, and ſee him take his leuell and diſcharge to a good purpoſe: as alſo he ſhall fee the Shotte keepe their order, as well in going on as in retyring; if he be found with other Troopes, he ſhall follow the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of him that commands the Troope, and carefully looke to the order of that part on which he is aſſigned to attend.</p>
                  <p>The eldeſt Sergeant ſhall lodge in the skirt of the Quarter right behind the Captayne, and the other Sergeant in the ſame ſort right beyond the Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20759:11"/>and in the Quarter they are both to viſite the Souldiers lodgings, and to ſee them orderly and quiet.</p>
                  <p>He is alſo to ſetch the Word from the Sergeant Maior of the Regiment, and deliuer it to his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, Lieutenant, and Enſigne, and to the Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall that is of the Watch; if the whole company watch, he is to attend, and to ſee the places where the Centenels are put out, and to viſite them all: if they watch by Squadrons, then hee ſhall lead the ſquadrons to bring them to their Guard, where hee ſhal attend vpon any extraordinary occaſion by the appointment of the Captaine of the Watch; and whilſt hee is there, he is to aduertiſe the Captaine of the watch, of any extrordinary diſcouery or acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of any importance.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall deliuer ſuch Munitions either of victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als or of warre to the Corporals of the Company, as hee ſhall receiue or fetch from the Sergeant Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor of the Regiment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Office of a Corporall of a Company.</head>
                  <p>THough it very ſeldome happen that he hath charge of the Company, yet if ſuch an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſhould fall out, that all the ſuperiour Officers were abſent, then the command doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to him.</p>
                  <p>To his place belongeth properly, the command of one Squadron of the Company, which hee is to deuide into Comradoes or Fellowſhips, to ſee all that are within that ſquadron wel exerciſed in their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20759:12"/>Armes, to keepe them and weare them Souldier-like, to deliuer munitions of Victuals or Armes, to gouerne the Watch, worke, or Seruice; and to take care in euery reſpect, that they doe the Duties of good Souldiers.</p>
                  <p>When the Drum beateth to the gathering of the Company, the Corporals are immediatly to bee in readineſſe themſelues, and to call together their Squadrons, with the which they ſhall repayre to their Colours, and if any of their Squadrons bee wanting without leaue, they ſhall giue notice ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to their Captaine, and ſhall proſecute the ſaid abſence to the puniſhing of them.</p>
                  <p>Hee ſhall haue at the leaſt, a third part of the Company vnder his Squadron, which being deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into Files, hee himſelfe ſhall bee Leader of the chiefe File, and with the ſame, alwayes to take place on the right hand of his Squadron, which ſhall bee compounded of one of the two ſorts of Armes now in vſe: Pikes, and Muskets.</p>
                  <p>Hee ſhall not (in caſe of any default by abſence) leaue the place voyd &amp; vnſupplyed, vnleſſe the ſame fall out to be the Leader or bringer vp, whoſe place ſhall be euer ſupplyed by the next.</p>
                  <p>In Marching and Fighting, the Corporall of the Company hath no command, but of the File which each of them leades; They are to ſee to the opening of their Files and Ranckes, and to the doubling of the ſame, to follow the ſound of the Drum, and to obſerue euery other Motion that ſhall be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the chiefe Officer; alwayes prouided, that he ſtart not out of his place, nor vſe any command of himſelfe.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:20759:12"/>
                  <p>When the Squadron is to Watch, he ſhall at the ſound of the Drum aſſemble them and repayre to his Enſigne, and ſhall ſee them fully furniſhed of their Armes, Powder, Match, Bullets, and all things elſe, that ſhall be neceſſary to the Armes they carry, whereof they ſhall be ſupplyed by the Sergeant of the Company.</p>
                  <p>Hee is to be lead by his Sergeant to the place of his Watch, and from him to receiue the Word and Directions, in what manner and where hee ſhall place his Centenels, as well by day as by night, which he is to ſee performed.</p>
                  <p>His Centinels being placed, hee is to let none paſſe his Guard without the word, vnleſſe the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the watch or the Sergeant Major, to whom after he knoweth them, he is to deliuer the Word, the firſt round onely.</p>
                  <p>In taking the Word, hee is neuer to goe further forth then to the Centinell next his Guard, and when the outermoſt Centinell giueth him warning of the approach of any, hee is to make his Guard ſtand to their Armes, and to take three or foure out among them, and ſo attend their comming, hauing giuen direction to his outermoſt Centinels for that end, to let them paſſe; when they are approached neare him, he is not to aduance out to them, but to call out one of the company, if more then one come together to him, and ſo receiue the Word from him, within the defence of thoſe three or foure Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers he tooke with him, who ſhall haue their Pikes charged, and their Matches cokt, till ſuch time as the Corporall hath receiued the Word,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20759:13"/>and giues them order to let them paſſe.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall ſo deuide his Centinels, that euery mans taske may bee alike; hee ſhall ſee them changed at due times, and ſhall now and then viſite them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked for; hee muſt warne his Centinels not to giue falſe Alarmes, but with as ſilent noyſe as is poſſible, to aduertiſe his ſaid Corporall; who vpon any extraordinary occaſion, ſhall make his Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron ſtand to their Armes, and giue notice of the danger diſcouered to the next Guards, and to the Captaine of the Watch.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall make good the place of his Guard, till he bee called from thence, and not ſuffer any of his Squadron to leaue the ſame till he be releeued; and he ſhall fulfill on his Guard, all Commands that ſhall be publiſhed for the entring or going forth of the Souldiers.</p>
                  <p>At the comming of the reliefe, hee ſhall put his Squadron into Armes, and ſtand ready to receiue them, and when his Centinels are relieued, march to his Quarter.</p>
                  <p>If during the time of his Watch, any of his Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron ſhall haue offended, hee is to Commit them, and to acquaint his Captaine and chiefe Officers therewith.</p>
                  <p>If by any occaſion of the Companies remoue, he be drawne from his Guard before the 24. houres bee expired, and that the Company lodge againe within the ſaid time, then ſhall the ſaid Corporall with his ſaid Squadron, bee in readineſſe to watch out the reſidue of the time, in ſuch place as he ſhall be appointed.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:20759:13"/>
                  <p>Laſtly, as the Corporall is next in degree to the Sergeant, ſo in behauing himſelfe well, he may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the place of a Sergeant, when by any acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent it ſhall be voyde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Office of a Lanſpreado.</head>
                  <p>NExt to the Corporall is the Lanſpreado, who in the abſence of the Corporall, is in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery reſpect to doe his Office; his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place is to leade the left hand File of the Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, and to haue of his owne, and the Files adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the ſame care for the obſeruing of their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as is ſpecified in the Corporals Office.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Office of a Drum.</head>
                  <p>THere ought to bee two Drums in a Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and both perfect in euery neceſſary ſound thereof, who by turnes are to doe all the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices belonging to the place; and therefore in Field or in Garriſon, one of them is euer to giue atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance in the Quarters, though the Company ſhould at any time be freed of their dutie.</p>
                  <p>The Drum hauing warning to beat to the gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the company, ſhall goe ſounding from one end of the Quarter to the other, twice, and ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre to his Enſignes lodging.</p>
                  <p>When the Company marcheth, one of them ſhall ſound by turnes: they ſhall one relieue the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>When the Company ſhall bee joyned with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20759:14"/>the Drummes ſhall take place by the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Drum Major, and ſhall ſound the ſame point, and obſerue the ſame time that the Drum doth that is next to the Colonell or chiefe Officer.</p>
                  <p>It is the office of a Drum, when any of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany are taken Priſoners, to enquire after them, and to carry their Ranſome, which he may boldly doe, after he hath receiued a Paſport from the Generall, or chiefe Commander of Army or Garriſon, where the Company is. When hee is come neere to any place of the Enemies, hee is to ſound thrice, and not to approach too neere, till hee be ſetcht in by ſome of the Enemy; hee is onely to make his arrant knowne, and not to diſcouer any thing of the ſtate of the place whence hee is ſent, that may be preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall to it: and to take as much notice as hee can of all ſuch thinges as concerneth the Enemy, which at his comming backe he ſhall diſcouer to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall or chiefe Officer.</p>
                  <p>It is his duty being in Garriſon and haue the maine Guard, not to goe off without leaue of the Captaine of the Watch, and to bee there all Night to beat an Alarme if need require, for which vſe he muſt bee perfect to practice on his ſtickes, becauſe the Enemy ſhall take no notice thereof. Hee muſt beate the Reliefe in the Morning after day breake, and to ſet the Parado, and at Night to beate Tapto before the Patrole goe aboue.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:20759:14"/>
               <head>The Office of a Troupe of Horſe.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Captayne of Horſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Captaine of a Troupe of Horſe, muſt take pleaſure to bee neatly Armed and well mounted, to giue thereby an example to his Souldiers to doe the like: hee muſt take care that his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers bee practuall in performing their Duties, and obſeruing Military Diſcipline, as hee himſelfe muſt be in obſeruing Orders, and executing the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections that are giuen or ſent him from his Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours; not fayling of the houre appointed him to be at the place aſſigned, with his Company.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall take care to teach his Souldiers the vſe of their Armes, and ſee them perfect therein, and alſo that they keepe their orders in Marching or Imbattelling; that they vnderſtand all motions which the Horſe are commanded to learne, as alſo the ſound of the Trumpet, to which end, hee ſhall haue his times of exerciſing his men whilſt he is in Garriſon.</p>
                  <p>In all occaſions he is to be firſt on Horſebacke, to ſee his Company kept vp in their full number, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20759:15"/>repleniſhed with all able Souldiers, to bee able to diſtinguiſh from the reſt, that are of moſt valour and courage, as alſo to bee ready to aſſiſt and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance them in all occaſions: ſo alſo is he to caſhere and diſmiſſe from the Company, ſuch Souldiers as hee findes fearefull, lazie, and vnfit for Seruice.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, he is to haue (if it be poſſible) two or three Souldiers in his Company, that are expert in the Countrey and wayes thereof eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a frontier place, that vpon all occaſions hee may haue Guides of his owne at hand, and ready to ſerue him; to which men, he ought to giue ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing extraordinary aboue the reſt.</p>
                  <p>In Marching to his Guard or though any place, hee is to be in the head of his Company before the Cornet, as alſo going towards an Enemie.</p>
                  <p>In Lodging, hee is to lodge in the head of the Troupe.</p>
                  <p>In Imbattelling, with other Troupes, he is to take ſuch place, as his ſuperiour Officer doe aſſigne him.</p>
                  <p>When the Lances are joyned with Curaſiers, or Harquebuſiers, the Captaine of the Lances com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the other, and in his abſence, the Captaine of the Curaſiers; in both their abſence, the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Harquebuſiers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Lieutenant of Horſe.</head>
                  <p>IT is neceſſary, that the Lieutenants of Horſe, ſhould bee men of great experience, abilitie and valour, ſuch as haue beene nourished &amp; brought vp amongſt the Cauolery: ordinarily thoſe that are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20759:15"/>aduanced to theſe places, are ſuch Souldiers, that in occaſion haue giuen better proofe of their owne perſons and valour, then the reſt; that haue paſſed through the other inferiour degrees to that charge, hauing beene Corporals or Cornets.</p>
                  <p>Hee is to be aſſiſtant to the Captaine, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of all directions and orders; and in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Captaine, to command the Troupe, many times hauing all the difficulties of affaires and occaſions laid vpon him, in regard that the Horſe troupes, are often giuen to young Genetle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of Noble houſes, that of themſelues haue ſmall experience.</p>
                  <p>The Lieftenant muſt be ſtrict and ſeuere to his Souldiers, making them doe their duties, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer elſe is neceſſary (preciſely and punctually) and alſo to take care, that they looke diligently to their Horſes, and to their Armes.</p>
                  <p>He marcheth alwayes in the Reere of the Troupe, taking care that the Souldiers follow the Captaine in their order and due diſtances, and that they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band not from the Troupe.</p>
                  <p>In occaſions of Fight, the Leiftenant is to keepe himſelfe firme in the Reere of his Troupe with his Sword in his hand, to incourage the Souldiers to doe their duties: and ſeeing any of them turning or ſhrinking, to flye from the Troupe, let him kill him, to giue incouragement to the reſt.</p>
                  <p>But if in the abſence of his Captaine there be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented any occaſion of fight, or that he be to march through ſuſpected places, the Leiftenant muſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance vp to the Front into the Captaines place, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20759:16"/>in his place behinde ſome Officer reformed, or ſome other perſon of valour in whom he hath confidence, which may diſcharge the duty of a Leiftenant.</p>
                  <p>The Troupe marching ordinarily, or paſſing through any place, or going to the place of Armes to the <hi>Parado,</hi> the Leiftenant muſt in no ſort take the place of the Captaine, but remaine alwaies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde as aforeſaid, becauſe the Lances and Cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiers haue their Cornets, who alwayes march in the head, and lead the Troupes.</p>
                  <p>But in Troups of Harquebuſiers that haue no Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets; the Leiftenant in abſence of his Captaine, is to take his Captaines place in the head of the Troupes, be it in marching, fighting, or drawing to the place of Armes, as to al other places, ſending to the Reere two of his beſt Corporalls, to doe the office of the Leiftenant; himſelfe now and then notwithſtanding turning towards the Reere, to ſee if the Souldiers march in order as they ſhould.</p>
                  <p>He muſt reade and write, that he may keepe a Liſt of the names and ſurnames of the Souldiers of his Troupe, ſo as any order being ſent him by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or receiuing Letters from his ſuperiours, he be not conſtrained to ſhew them to others: he muſt alſo know the abilitie and ſufficiency of each Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, to the end, that there being any occaſion to ſend them out to any place, he may know whom he may beſt vſe and imploy.</p>
                  <p>The Troupe marching to the guard, and being approched neere vnto the place, the Leiftenant is to goe before to view the court of Guard; and by the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20759:16"/>Leiftenant, who is to be releeued; be informed of the place of Centinels, both of the day, and of the night, what the wayes are he muſt beate: and of all other things that by order he is to doe it in that place.</p>
                  <p>The Leiftenant is bound to place the Centinels himſelfe, and to viſit them oftentimes, ſparing no diligence, keeping himſelfe in particuler, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally armed, and his Horſe bridled.</p>
                  <p>The Troupe being lodged in any village, the Leiftenant muſt take the Billets of the quarter-Maſter of the Troupe, and afterwards diſtribute them himſelfe to the Souldiers, with as much order and contentment to them as he can before the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets lodging, who is to make an halt or ſtand there with the Troupe, and attend the foreſaid diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Billets, to the end that vpon any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or when any Alarme happens, the Souldiers may know whereto come together, and ioyne themſelues to their Cornet: if they ſhall tarry lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then one day in a place, the Leiftenant is to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit the Horſes, to ſee how the Souldiers gouerne themſelues, and that they indamage not their Hoſtes; which if he finde, to remedy, making the Captaine acquainted with euery thing: and when afterwards they doe diſlodge, the Leiftenant muſt command their fires to be put out, and ſee it perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
                  <p>Going to lodge in any Village or Fort, or to be in Garriſon, that the Leiftenant ought ſo to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo date the extraordinary reformed Officers, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers according to their merits: In all places where
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20759:17"/>they lodge more then once aday; the Leiftenant ſhall write the names of the Souldiers vpon the Billets, and ſhall keepe a Regiſter of thoſe Billets, that when their Hoſts ſhall come to make any complaint, he may readily finde their names, and chaſtiſe them as he ſees cauſe.</p>
                  <p>When the Troupe is to march, and that the Trumpets ſound to horſe, the Leiftenant muſt bee firſt in order and on horſe-backe, taking care that all the Souldiers doe the like with diligence: and if he finde any of them negligent in this point, be it either through an ill cuſtome, or of purpoſe to loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter behinde and pillage the houſes, he muſt puniſh them preſently with all ſeuerity, for an axample to others.</p>
                  <p>It is neceſſary for the Leiftenant to haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the country and of the waies, there happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning many occaſions that he is to ſend out to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer, and beate the coaſts about; the commodity of Guides not being at all times found.</p>
                  <p>In caſe the Troupe be charged by the Enemie, the Leiftenant with ſome few Souldiers, being beſt mounted, muſt ſtay behinde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Cornet.</head>
                  <p>THe Cornet in the abſence of the Captaine and Leiftenant, commaunds the Troupe.</p>
                  <p>In marching, he goes alwayes in the head of the Troupe (yet behinde the Captaine) who muſt ſuffer no man to march beyond the <hi>Standard,</hi> or to be equall with him.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:20759:17"/>
                  <p>In occaſion of fight, the Cornet of a company of Lances ſhall take his place on the left hand of the Captaine, and equall in front with him, and going to the Shocke together with him, muſt indeuour to breake his Cornet or Standerd vpon the Enemy: which Standard falling ſo to the ground, he is not to take care to take it vp; and if any man ſhall take it vp and reſtore it him againe, he muſt not put it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vpon his Staffe: nor no new in the place, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the permiſſion of the Generall.</p>
                  <p>In occaſion of fight with foote, the Cornet of Lances muſt likewiſe breake his Standard vpon the ſame foote, but neither vpon Foote nor Horſe that is turned and running away.</p>
                  <p>The Cornet of Curaſiers in marching goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the troupe with his Cornet, as alſo when hee preſenteth himſelfe in the place of Armes, and when hee is to ſalute, he is to doe it in the ſame manner as the Cornet of Lances doth.</p>
                  <p>In the time of fight, the Cornet of Curaſiers, is to take his place in the middle of the Troupe, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning behinde him the two third parts of the Troupe, and the other part that is before, muſt bee thoſe that be beſt armed, and the beſt men.</p>
                  <p>The Cornet ought to keepe a Liſt of the names of the Souldiers of the Troupe.</p>
                  <p>In all occaſions of Mutiny, diſcord, and diſputes, he is preſently to informe his Captaine and Leifte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and to be aſſiſtant to the Captaine and Leifte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, or either of them, in ſeeing all directions per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that are commanded by a ſuperiour Officer; as alſo, all ſuch as the Captaine hath authority to command.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:20759:18"/>
                  <head>The Quarter Maſter his Office.</head>
                  <p>THe Quarter Maſter is to fetch the word euery night, and the directions from the Sergeant Maior of the Horſe: he is to diſtribute the Billets among the Souldiers, and was wont to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deliuer out their pay vnto them, which now is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen out by the Leiftenant of the Troupe, though in my opinion not ſo well; for it were much better, that the Captaine or Leiftenant ſhould call the Quarter Maſter apart, appointing him the manner how he ſhould pay the Souldiers, to leaue the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of it to him; which without doubt would giue greater contentment, becauſe the Souldier in this point of his accompt, may ſpeake more freely with the Quarter Maſter, then the other Officers; who by this meanes alſo, are deliuered from a great many harſh replyes, which they muſt ordinarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue from the Souldiers, to the diminiſhing the reſpect they ought to beare them.</p>
                  <p>He is to attend the Quarter Maſter Generall, and to take his orders from him of lodging the Troupe, carrying with him one or two Souldiers, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him by the Leiftenant, that he may the better aduertiſe the Troupe where they ſhall lodge.</p>
                  <p>In the abſence of the Cornet, Leiftenant, and Captaine, he is to command the Company.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:20759:18"/>
                  <head>Trumpet.</head>
                  <p>THere ought to be two Trumpets in euery Troupe of Horſe, who ought to be diligent to ſound preciſely at the times appointed: one of them is to be euer with the Cornet vpon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions.</p>
                  <p>When the Troupe doth march, they goe before the Captaine in the head of the Troupe, and in fight in the flancke of the Troups.</p>
                  <p>In Lodging, the one lodgeth with the Captaine, the other with the Cornet.</p>
                  <p>Going out of their lodging, either on foot or on Horſe-backe, they are neuer to leaue off their Trumpets, but alwayes to haue it by them.</p>
                  <p>They are imployed in Meſſages for Priſoners, and other occaſions to the Enemie, and therefore ought to bee intelligent men and well gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that they may be able to diſcouer, and at their returne to giue an accompt of any aduantage of diſorder or important things, they are able to learne among the Enemies; as alſo to keepe themſelues ſo as they diſcouer nothing that may offend their own party.</p>
                  <p>Briefly, many important ſeruices may be drawne from them, and good vſe made; prouided they bee diſcreet.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Corporall of Horſe.</head>
                  <p>THough there haue beene ſome, who are of opinion, that it is not neceſſary to haue a Corporall in a Troupe of Lances and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20759:19"/>Curaſiers, notwithſtanding I finde this Officer ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; for by the meanes of a Corporall, the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are better diſtributed; and they themſelues goe forth with the Leiftenant to aſſiſt him to place his Centinels, when it is the Souldiers turne of their Squadron to doe it: and in ſudden occaſion of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out a number of Souldiers, the eaſieſt way is to command a whole Squadron to the ſeruice: their lodgings alſo are made, and diſtributed with more facility: eſpecially when the Troupe is not lodged altogether in one place, and when there are few houſes to be diſtributed; the houſes being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed, ſo many to a Squadron, the Leiftenant giues the Billets thereof to each Squadron, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is to lodge his Souldiers.</p>
                  <p>In Troups of Harquebufiers, we vſe no Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls; and they are of better eſteeme, becauſe they haue euer beene there: and the Hargubuſiers going many times in ſmall Troups; the Corporals haue therefore ordinarily more imployment then the Launces or Curaſiers.</p>
                  <p>The Troupes of Harquebuſiers doe ordinarily battle (leaſt rude) and ſerue for the Vandguard, it belonging to them to ſend forth their Auant Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers; which charge is giuen to one of the Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls, which muſt bee a man of good experience; that he muſt be able to know how to acquit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in a charge of that importance.</p>
                  <p>If it be neceſſary to guard a Paſſage or place of importance, the cuſtome is to ſend a Corporall with his Squadron thither.</p>
                  <p>In occaſions of fight, we are wont to ſend out
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20759:19"/>Corporals with their whole Squadrons to the skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, after the Lieutenant is firſt gone out for that purpoſe: for hee is alwayes the firſt.</p>
                  <p>The Corporals ought to reade and write, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are to keepe a liſt of the Souldiers of their Squadrons, to the end hee may diſtribute vnto them equally their Duties.</p>
                  <p>The Captaines are conformable to allow vnto the Corporals, an halfe part of the forrage; and giue them the tenth part in a hundred.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:20759:20"/>
               <head>The Dignitie of Souldiers in their Fyles.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the Ordering of a Foot Company, and of the Dignitie of each Souldier in their Fyle: With the manner of Exerciſing now vſed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, it is meete for diuers good reſpects, that your men bee deuided into Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, and the Soldiers of theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, into their Fyles.</p>
                  <p>Now a Fyle conſiſteth of ten Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers armed alike, whereof euery one knoweth his place, all of them ſtanding in a direct line downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and behind one another, and comprehended betweene the Leader and the bringer vp.</p>
                  <p>It is likewiſe neceſſary, for the giuing of due ſtrength and reciprocall proportion, that the men of each ſort of Armes bee ſo indifferently deuided, both for the number and qualitie of the men, that in euery of the ſaid Fyles there may be an equall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution, both of the better and worſer ſort.</p>
                  <p>This may be done, (the number of men being firſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20759:20"/>knowne, and how many of each ſort of Armes you haue) by chooſing firſt out of euery of the ſaid ſorts, ſo many of the beſt men as the whole number will make Fyles through, ſo many ſecond, and ſo onwards, ſtill chooſing of the better ſort, till the tenth man bee choſen.</p>
                  <p>The men thus choſen ſhall be deuided in manner as followeth:</p>
                  <p>The firſt choiſe, becauſe they are men of beſt worth, ſhall ſtand in the Front, and command the reſt of the Fyle, and theſe men are to be knowne by the name of Leaders.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe of the ſecond choiſe, becauſe they are next in account, are to ſtand in the Reere or laſt place of the tenne, and are to bee knowne by the name of Bringers vp.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe of the third and fourth choiſe, are to take the fifth and ſixth places in the Fyle, and are to bee knowne by the names of Middlemen; to wit, the fifth, the Leaders middle-man, the ſixth, the Brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers vp middle-man.</p>
                  <p>The fifth, ſixth, and ſeauenth choiſe, to be ranged in the ſecond, third, and fourth places.</p>
                  <p>The eighth, ninth, and tenth choiſe, to bee in the ſeauenth, eight, and ninth places: by which diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it falls out, that the tenth and laſt place of men (reckoning from the firſt downeward) taketh the ninth place of the Fyle.</p>
                  <p>Theſe men thus deuided into Fyles, it will be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the effecting of theſe thinges, that be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by this Diſcipline; That as the Souldiers haue their places in the Fyles according to the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20759:21"/>worth of each man, ſo the Fyles themſelues ſhould haue their particuler degrees and places; to which end, the Companies ſhall likewiſe conſiſt of tenne Fyles, which ſhall take their places one by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Front and Rancke, as the Souldiers in euery Fyle did before in Depth.</p>
                  <p>Following which courſe, the firſt Fyle ſhall ſtand on the right hand of the reſt; the ſecond Fyle in Dignitie, ſhall ſtand on the left hand, outermoſt of the tenth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">To bee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were not better to reckon your degrees at the 8. th, 9. th, and tenth Fyle.</note>The third, and fourth in Dignitie, ſhall take the fifth, and ſixth places, being in the middle places of the tenne.</p>
                  <p>The fifth, ſixth, and ſeauenth, ſhall ſtand in the ſecond, third, and fourth places, reckoning from the right hand toward the middle Fyle.</p>
                  <p>The eight, ninth, and tenth Fyle, in the ſeaunth, eighth, and ninth places, from the left hand Fyle to the middle Fyle; So that in euery Fyle, the tenth and laſt man in Dignitie ſtandeth in the ninth place, reckoning from the Leaders downward: &amp; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond in value, the tenth and laſt place. So among the Fyles, the tenth, which is the Fyle of leaſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, taketh the ninth place, reckoning from the right hand Fyle, which is the firſt in Dignitie and account; and the ſecond in Dignitie holds the tenth place, being the outermoſt on the left hand, as the firſt is on the right.</p>
                  <p>Theſe tenne Fyles, I would haue knowne ſtill by their degrees of Value: as firſt, ſecond, third, fourth, fifth, ſixth, ſeauenth, eighth, ninth, and tenth, and not by the places they ſtand in when they are
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20759:21"/>ranged, which notwithſtanding may ſerue guide the men to their places, becauſe they neuer change their ſtandings.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Dignitie of Leaders.</head>
                  <p>ANd as the Soldiers in euery Fyle ſhall take no place till their Leaders ſet forward, at which time they are all to follow ſucceſſiuely, as they are to ſtand in the fyle that the laſt man may fall hindermoſt; ſo none of the fyles ſhall take place till the firſt fyle hath taken his, and then the reſt as they are to ſtand the one by another to take their places, ſo that ſtill the outermoſt fyle to the left hand, is to take his place laſt: which ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner being obſerued and due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly executed,

<note place="margin">
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>2.</cell>
                              <cell>6.</cell>
                              <cell>10.</cell>
                              <cell>8.</cell>
                              <cell>4.</cell>
                              <cell>3.</cell>
                              <cell>7.</cell>
                              <cell>9.</cell>
                              <cell>5.</cell>
                              <cell>1.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell cols="10"> 
                                 <hi>Front Leaders.</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </note>
men are ranged in an inſtant, without any confuſion or helpe of Officers.</p>
                  <p>Now as in Fyles the dutie of the Middle-man is to keepe thoſe before him in a right line,

<note place="margin">
                        <lg>
                           <l>1 0.</l>
                           <l>5 0.</l>
                           <l>9 0.</l>
                           <l>7 0.</l>
                           <l>3 0.</l>
                           <l>4 0.</l>
                           <l>8 0.</l>
                           <l>10 0.</l>
                           <l>0 6.</l>
                           <l>2 0.</l>
                        </lg> The Dignity of men in their Fyle.</note>

and for the Bringer vp to doe the like, to the middle-men and thoſe before them; As alſo, if diuers fyles bee joyned in one body together to keepe in euen rancke with the others; ſo are the Leaders of the Fyles alſo, in the Front to keepe euen with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and with the other Troupes when any march in or Front with them, and to obſerue like diſtances in their fyles, and to take care either Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching or going to Charge, to keepe ſuch Diſtances in the body they make; as may bee beſt for eaſe, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20759:22"/>for the ſafetie of the men, wherein the two out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt fyles are to vſe the greateſt obſeruance.</p>
                  <p>The Fyles being ranged, the foure chiefe Leaders (to wit) the right, leſt, and the two middle Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, are to take care that the Front bee kept euen, and that the Diſtances in all motions, together with the Motions themſelues, bee duly obſerued; which is eaſily performed when theſe ſoure keepe euen: for the right Leader and his middle Leader, may ſee that the three Leaders betwixt them doe their duties, and the left hand Leader with his middle Leader, the other three betwixt them.</p>
                  <p>Now reſteth to teach, what bee the other parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer Duties of the Leaders, Bringers vp, and Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle-men of the Fyles; as alſo what the Duties of thoſe Leaders, who in the Body of the tenne Fyles are to doe their Office to the Body, as the others are to euery fyle apart. The Leaders of the fyle ought to be as followeth: As he is the Chiefe of the ten, ſo is he to be reſpected and obeyed by them in theſe thinges: they are to ſhew themſelues in their Armes when bee requireth it; aſwell becauſe it is his Office to ſee them kept cleane, as to teach them the true vſe of their Armes: to acquaint them how euery one is to take his place in the fyle, to make them perfect in all manner of Duties, as March, Motions, Fight, Workes, Diſtances, and Meaſures: as alſo to inſtruct them in the vnderſtanding of all Commandements, by Drum or by voyce, or by any other Signall appointed: as alſo how to behaue themſelues in making their Quarter, and making their Cabbins, wherein hee himſelfe when he is joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20759:22"/>with other fyles, is by his owne due obſeruance of the Directions giuen, to ſhew them the way, and make himſelfe their example.</p>
                  <p>The Bringer vp, as hee is the ſecond in worth, ſo ought hee to be the ſecond in eſtimation, and to be held as the Lieutenant of the Fyle (not onely to aſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt the Leader in euery thing of his Dutie, and in his ſickneſſe or abſence to execute his Office) but to take care alſo, his fyle being ranged with a Body of Fyles, that his fyle keepe his order duely, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, that halfe that is next him: for the Bringers vp are of ſpeciall vſe in March, Motion, and Fight, as alſo the Middle-men; in part becauſe they ſtand apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the gouerning of the Fyle, hauing euery diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order in their eye: And if by the turning the Front to the Reere, there be occaſion to reſiſt in the Reere, or by Deuiding the one halfe (as it falls out many times) both in Front and Reere, then is hee in all thinges to demeane himſelfe, as is before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Dutie of Leaders.</p>
                  <p>As for the Middle-men, they are not onely for Diſtinction ſake, (though it bee the chiefe end) but are vpon the Deuiding of the body, ſometimes to doe the dutie of Leaders, more often of Bringers vp, becauſe they cloſe the Reere of each Deuiſion, and are to ſee thoſe of their fyles before them doe their Duties; But if the Body bee to bend all his force forwards, then is the Middle-man of the fiſt place to Diſcharge himſelfe, as is before mentioned, and to ſee that the three Souldiers before him doe their Duties by keeping their Orders, filling and ſupplying the places of the ſlaine Souldiers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20759:23"/>them, and the Enemy being broken, it is their Duties to ſtirre them vp to follow the chaſe ſharply.</p>
                  <p>The Middle-man of the ſixt place, is vpon the time of a Charge, to leaue a little ſpace betwixt the other Middle man and himſelfe, vnleſſe it bee thought neceſſary to ſupport the firſt Shocke of the Enemy, by ſtanding cloſely joyned.</p>
                  <p>In Fight, both Leaders, Bringers vp, Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and all the reſt in generall, are to keepe their Diſtances in Fyle and Rancke, diligently to bee ſilent; and attentiue to the voyce of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to obſerue the meaſures of March and Skirmiſh duly, not to bend their Weapons or offer Fight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they may well do it, as alſo not to forbeare it or performe it lazily when time ſerueth, not to leaue his place through Cowardiſe or ſence of ſlight hurts, to ſucceed willingly and readily in the emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie place before him, the Souldier that poſſeſſed it being ſlaine, or grieuoſly hurt, and no longer able to reſiſt: not to leaue their places for the carrying away of their fellowes that are hurt; not to ſtep vntimely, or preſſe ouer haſtily to the Fight, either exceeding the meaſure of the March, or before the Souldier before him, by giuing backe, ſhew that hee cannot make his place good any longer.</p>
                  <p>This ſhall ſatisfie at this time for the Duties of the Leaders, Bringers vp, and Middle-men, with the reſt of the Fyles in a Company; wee will now goe forwards to the Diſtances and Motions, with which they are to be acquainted.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:20759:23"/>
                  <head>Of Diſtances.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The diſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are all to be reckned from the Centinels of the ſouldiers: that is, from the midſt of the ſpace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the one mans feet, to the midſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans feet, that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders with him.</note>FOr auoyding of confuſion, it ſhall be good to ſet downe before we goe any further, what Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances you are to obſerue betweene the Ranks &amp; the Fyles; which I would haue only three (to wit) open order; order, &amp; cloſe order: your firſt Diſtance is your open order, when your men both in Ranke and Fyle, ſtand remoued ſixe foot in ſquare from one another; which Diſtance you are alwaies to range your Troupe, when you will exerciſe your Motions.</p>
                  <p>Your ſecond diſtances is your order, which is, when the Souldiers in their rankes and Fyles, ſtand three foot remoued aſunder, which is vſed when you will imbattaile your Troups, and lead them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Enemie, or when you come to ſtand, or meane to wheele the Body: For when you march, you are to obſerue three foot betweene the Fyles, and ſixe betweene the Ranks, vnleſſe you march with your Pikes aduanced, in which caſe you may keepe your meaner order of fixe foot in ſquare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Becauſe the meaſure of this Diſtance cannot be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſo iuſtly by the Eye, we take the diſtance of ſixe foot betweene Fyle and Fyle, by commanding the Souldiers to ſtretch forth their armes, and ſtand ſo remoued one from another, that their hands may touch, and for the Rankes we make account, we take the ſame Diſtance of ſixe foot, when the butt end of the Pikes doe almoſt reach the heeles of thoſe that march before them.</note>Your third and laſt diſtance, is your cloſe order, when the Fyles ioyne ſhoulder to ſhoulder; and the rancks come vp to the Swords point, which is of vſe in ſome kindes of motion; but chiefly when you will make the Troups ſeeme leſſe, or in the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20759:24"/>of ſome ſtraight, or when of neceſ forced to breake through an Enemy, or when you receaue a charge of Horſe, or of Foot, that purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to breake through you.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">We take the ſecond order or diſtance of 3. foote from Fyle to Fyle, by bidding the Souldiers to ſet their armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenbowe, and ioyne themſelues ſo cloſe, that their Elbows meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and the Ranks when they come vp almoſt to the ſwords point.</note>When you meane to charge, you muſt aduance your Pikes, and cloſe your rankes, to the diſtance of three foot; and when the ſignall or word to charge is giuen; then the rankes muſt cloſe to the Swords point; but this cloſing of the Swordes point, is to bee vnderſtood, of the fiue firſt rankes, which makes vp halfe the depth of the body; for though the whole body doc aduance their Pikes, and cloſe their rankes, to the diſtance three foot; yet vpon the ſignall of charge, the fiue laſt rankes ſhall neither couch, or charge their Pikes; nor cloaſe to their cloſe order, vnleſſe there be an expreſſe command for it, which command, as I ſaid before, is neuer to be deliuered, but when a great Shocke is giuen or ſuſtained; and then it is of vſe, for the holding and ſholdring forward of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt fiue rankes: and as I take it, will be performed with eaſe and ſtrength, whilſt their Pikes are aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; for it were bootleſſe for thoſe to bend, that are without reach of an Enemy, beſides the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in the vſe of theſe fiue rankes: if you ſhould be charged in the Reere, or vpon any other occaſion, and therefore in this ſort would I haue the laſt fiue rankes, with their Pikes aduanced, to attend the opportunity of fighting.</p>
                  <p>Both the heauy Armed, and the light Armed, are to bee made acquainted with theſe diſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; there are alſo other Diſtances, which I
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20759:24"/>would haue the light Armed accuſtomed to: and thoſe likewiſe are of three ſorts, as the former, which I would haue diſtinguiſhed by the great, the meane, and the leſſe: of your open orders, the great thirtie foot betweene Fyle and Fyle, the meane twentie foot, and the leſſe fifteene foot: but though the rankes alwayes obſerue three foot; onely the men in the Fyles are to ſide, or ſtand ſtooping, either to the right or left hand Diaginall to the diſtance: the Fyles are ranged, in either 3. feet, 2. feet, or 1 ½ feet to the hand required, or ſhall be demonſtrated in his place, where I purpoſe to declare the vſe of theſe Diſtances, and my meaning herein: your Musketiers are neuer to be cloſer, then your meane order of three foot in ſquare, becauſe they are to haue a free vſe of their Armes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Generall motions which the Company or Troupes are to obſerue.</head>
                  <p>NOw that I haue framed the Body, in manner as you haue ſeene, &amp; particularly inlarged euery part thereof, with the diſtances to be vſed and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in all occaſions; I may boldly proceed to the orderly mouing of the ſame, which I would gladly ſo effect, that the whole Body or Troupe ſhould moue as nimbly, and with as ſmall confuſion, as the body of man: which by the due execution of that which followes, may be in many performed. But before I proceed to deliuer the Motions them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: I finde it requiſite to giue theſe three rules, which you are euer to obſerue.</p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:20759:25"/>
                  <p n="1">1. All commands are to bee deliuered in the Front whereſoeuer it be.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whenſoeuer the Flanck is made the Front; the ſhott that are now in the Front, and the Reere, ſhall remoue and fall vpon the Flancks, the right to the right, and the left to the left.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Whenſoeuer theſe words of direction (as you were) are propounded: it is meant thereby, that you are to returne by the contrary hand, to the place from whence you came; as for example: if you did turne to the right hand, you are to returne as you were to the left hand, and ſo in all other motions.</p>
                  <p>The motions of Troupes are two-fold, of the whole, or of part; of the perſon of a Souldier in his ſtation, or of the limmes of the body, conſtituted into Rankes or Fyles; and theſe either of keeping or leauing the place they ſtand in: In that of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping their places, the men only turne their bodyes, the way which is commanded them: in that of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their places, the whole body moueth into an other place or a part thereof: which motions for the better vnderſtanding, wee will diſtinguiſh the Rankes and Fyles.</p>
                  <p>By Ranks, the body changing his place, but ſo as the Leader of the corner Fyle of that hand, to which the body wheeleth, turnes his body only that way the Manaple moueth, vnleſſe in doubling of Rankes wherein it is changed but in part, or by countermarching, which may be done, and the place kept: This is mouing by ranckes, which is to be vſed, when we deſire to keepe neere to our firſt ſtation.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:20759:25"/>
                  <p>By Fyles, howſoeuer each man in his owne place may alter, or the men in their Fyles may change their places; the Body or maine, keepeth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion ſtill, vnleſſe you make of the Flanke the Front, wherein though the Maniple retayneth his order and ſo much ground, yet not the ſame ground.</p>
                  <p>The motions of the perſon in his proper place are commanded by theſe termes of direction: (to wit) to the right hand: to the left hand: and to the right or left hand about, or to the Reere.</p>
                  <p>The motions of the lymbes, is properly ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, when only ſome of them doe moue, and the reſt doe ſtand: as in theſe words of commaund; Rankes to the right or left hand double: Fyles to the right or left hand double, Ranks cloſe forward; Ranks open backwards, Fyles to the right or left hand cloſe, or open to the diſtance you will haue them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">To the Right hand.</note>If you will make the right Flanke the Front, then are you to ſay, To the right hand: at the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of which words, the Souldiers are preſently to turne their faces that way; and ſo your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand will be performed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">To the Left hand.</note>In like ſort, if you will haue your left Flanke the Front, you muſt ſay: To the left hand; and preſently they will all turne their faces towards the left flancke: When you will reſtore them backe againe to their firſt aſpect, you muſt ſay; As you were.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">By the right or left hand to the Reere.</note>When you will make the Reere the Front, then are you to ſay; By the right hand about: or, by the left hand about, or to the Reere: at which words
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20759:26"/>euery Souldier is to turne his face to his backſide.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ranks cloſe.</note>When you will cloſe your Rankes, you muſt ſay, Ranks cloſe, which is alwayes to be vnderſtood, that all the Rankes moue at one inſtant cloſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, to the firſt ranke of Leaders, which is, to ſtand firme.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ranks open.</note>When you will open your ranks, you muſt ſay, Ranks open; by which is alwaies vnderſtood, they are to open backward, vnleſſe an expreſſe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to the contrary.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Fyles to the right or left hand cloſe.</note>So likewiſe, if you will cloſe the Fyles to any diſtance, you muſt ſay, Fyles to the right or left hand cloſe, to what order you pleaſe, and then all of them turning their faces to that hand giuen, moue ioyntly and wholly togeather, ſauing the outmoſt Fyle to that hand you cloſe, which is to ſtand firme till the Troupe haue gotten his diſtance, and if you will reſtore them, then you are to ſay; As you were.</p>
                  <p>When the commandement is giuen for the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering any of the Diſtances by Fyles,<note place="margin">Fyles cloſe.</note> without any expreſſe mention, to which hand they ſhould open or cloſe, Then the whole Troupe is to edge indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently, and at an inſtant to both hands, towards or from the middle ſpace betweene the two mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlemoſt Leaders. The words of commandment are Fyles cloſe,<note place="margin">Fyles open.</note> Fyles open.</p>
                  <p>There be two ſorts of doubling: The one by Ranks, the other by Fyles, and both theſe are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed diuers wayes as ſhall be ſhewed.</p>
                  <p>When an Enemie goeth about to diſcloſe you with the ouer-breadth of his body, it will bee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for you then to increaſe or double your
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20759:26"/>Front, which may be done either by Rankes, when euery ſecond ranke commeth betweene the diſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Ranke before it, and that either to the right, or to the left hand:<note place="margin">Doubling of Ranks to the right or left hand.</note> The word of Directions are: Ranks to the right or left hand double.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Middle-men to double their Ranks, or Front to right or left hand.</note>Or by the Middle-man when the laſt fiue Rankes doe march vp through the ſpaces betweene the Fyles, till the bringers vp, middle-men be euen in front with the Leaders: The words of command are; Middle-men to the right or left hand: Double your front.</p>
                  <p>Or by the bringers vp by Induction, which is, when the bringers vp doe aduance through the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances betweene the Fyles; and next after them, the next laſt Ranke, and ſo the reſt ſucceſſiuely, till the bringers vp bee in the ranke with the Leaders, and their Middle-men with the Leaders middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and ſo the ſecond, third,<note place="margin">Bringers vp to double their Rankes on the Fronts.</note> and fourth ranks from the front. The words of direction are; Bringers vp to the right or left hand, double the front.</p>
                  <p>Or by deuiſion, when the laſt fiue Rankes doe turne their faces, the one halfe in their fyles to the right hand, and the other halfe to the left hand, and ſo march forth from both the flancks, till they haue gotten ſuch a proportion of ground or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as is anſwerable to the order the firſt fiue Ranks doe ſtand in; and then preſently without at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending any further commandement, they turne their faces againe towards the front, and march vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both flanckes, till they come euen with the front;<note place="margin">Middle-men by Deuiſion double the Front.</note> The words of command; Middle-men by deuiſion, double the front.</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:20759:27"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Middle-men double the body.</note>This alſo may be performed to either hand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deuiding of the ranks, by the marching forth onely of the whole fiue rankes together: But in this caſe, the Shott on both flanks, or on either, muſt edge outward, till they haue giuen the Pikes a full diſtance to come vp betweene them and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt fiue rankes of Pykes: The words are, Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men double the body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Double the Front by the Hankes.</note>Or by ranke to either flanke, which is, when the ſecond ranke is drawne out euen with the ranke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it: The words are; Double the front by the flanks.</p>
                  <p>Or by halfe rankes, when euery ſecond ranke di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth it ſelfe, and increaſeth the former vpon each ſide.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Doubling of Fyles.</note>When you will haue the Body of greater depth; then you muſt cauſe the one fyle to mingle with the fiue other, either to the righ hand or to the left; which is termed doubling of fyles; and is perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med after this manner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Doubling of Fyles to the right or left hand.</note>If to the right hand, then is the outermoſt fyle to the right hand to ſtand, and the Leader of the ſecond fyle, ſhall ſide behinde the Leader of the firſt fyle: and ſo of all the reſt of the ſecond fyle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde thoſe of the outmoſt fyle ſucceſſiuely: ſo as the bringer vp of the ſecond fyle, ſhall come to ſtand behinde the bringer vp of the firſt fyle, and ſo likewiſe all the other fyles, by euery ſecond fyle: So that the ſecond, fourth, ſixt, eigth, and tenth, ſhall ſtand within, or goe into the firſt, third, fifth, ſeauenth and ninth: all which in a knowne number of fyles may be done at once without confuſion or diſorder.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:20759:27"/>
                  <p>But becauſe this manner of Doubling, in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry orderlieſt &amp; beſt performance, cannot but breake the Body, by reaſon of the diſioyning of Fyles: I would rather put the one halfe of the Fyles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde the other halfe, which may bee ſpeedily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, either by the aduancing of falling backe of the one halfe part of the Fyles: the wordes of Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction are; Fyle vpon fyle.</p>
                  <p>But if you deſire to keepe the ſame ground, then let the one halfe part of the fyle in the Body which is to Double, cloſe their Ranckes forwards towards the Leaders, to halfe the Diſtance they were in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commandement was giuen: And the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther halfe part of the fyles in the Body, to ſhorten their Diſtances toward the Reere, or Bringers vp, to halfe that they held backwards: By which meanes it will fall out, that the Leaders of the halfe which is to double, will ſtand a little beyond the Bringers vp of the other halfe: and by Edging of their fyles behind the other halfe, may eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme your Direction; The wordes of Command are theſe, Fyles double the Body to the right or left hand.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Counter-March.</head>
                  <p>COunter-Marches are two-fold, for either wee Counter-march the Ranckes, or the Fyles: and theſe either by changing your ground, or keeping ſtill the ſame ground. But though to ſhew the diuerſitie of them, the kindes are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by Rankes and Fyles; yet in the practice
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20759:28"/>you are to nominate neither, but are to ſay: To the right or to the left hand Counter-march.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Counter-march and looſe ground.</note>Counter-marching of Ranckes and altering of Ground are thus affected: When the Command is deliuered, the Leaders turne, and paſſe through the Diſtances betweene thc fyles; and when they are paſſed as farre beyond, the next Ranke turnes after them, and ſo ſucceſſiuely the reſt in due diſtance Marching out after their Leaders, till they haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken another like place from the Bringers vp, equall to that they did poſſeſſe, or otherwiſe paſſe on fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the diſcretion of the Commander.</p>
                  <p>The vſe is, when the Enemy ſhewes himſelfe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Reere, and you deſire to confront him with your beſt men; the wordes of Direction are: To the right or left hand Counter-march and paſſe: if you will keepe the ſame Ground, then thus: The Leaders vpon the Word giuen muſt turne as before and March through the Diſtances of the fyles, till they come betweene thc Diſtances where the Bringers vp ſtand; and ſo the reſt ſucceſſiuely. After them the Middle-men, the ranckes of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Middle-men ſtanding firme, till the fiue firſt Ranckes haue poſſeſſed the place betweene the laſt fiue, and doe by that meanes double them. Then the Middle-men to the Bringers vp without atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any further Command, ſhall march till they haue gotten the diſtance of the Rancks, which done, they ſhall take their place right behind the Leaders Middle-men: ſo the reſt likewiſe ſucceſſiuely, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching out after one another to the ſame diſtance, &amp; ſhal turne &amp; take their places till the Bringers vp get
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20759:28"/>the places the Leaders marched from, &amp; the Leaders the places where the Bringers vp ſtood: The words of direction; To the right or left hand Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>termarch and ſtand: The very ſame is done otherwiſe thus:</p>
                  <p>Aſſoone, as you haue giuen the word Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>march, and the Leaders begin to turne; at the ſame time and inſtant all the Body ſhall mooue forward, and the Ranckes aduance ſucceſſiuely one after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, ſtill turning after their Leaders as they come vp to the place from whence they mooued, and following them till the Leaders haue taken the place of the Bringers vp, and the Bringers vp bee come into the places of the Leaders; The words are: to the right or left hand Counter-march.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Counter-march by Fyles.</note>The Counter-marching of Fyles, for the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of it is nothing different from the former of Rankes; Onely, when you will Counter-march your Fyles, you muſt firſt bid them, to the right hand or left hand, and when they are turned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that flancke from whence you meant to Counter-march, you muſt ſay; To the right or left hand Counter-march.</p>
                  <p>The vſe is, when you will paſſe your Muſquetiers all to one flancke, or any Maniple or Maniples to any other Quarter of the Army, either from the right hand to the left, or to the middle Battell, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny contrary.</p>
                  <p>When you will Wheele the body or Maniple to the right hand, you muſt command the right hand Fyle to ſtand firme:<note place="margin">Wheeling the Body.</note> then Command them to the right hand; and all of them ſhall turne their faces that way, ſo as the whole Body will front towards the right flancke. Then ſay, Fyles to your order:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20759:29"/>and all of them ſhall cloſe forward toward the right fyle, at the diſtance of 3. foot, and this perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, bid them; Front as they were: Then ſay, Rankes to your Order: and all the Rankes ſhall cloſe forward to 3. foot. And this being effected, Command the right Leader to ſtand firme like the fixed foot of a Compaſſe; and all the reſt plumpe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to Wheele to the right hand about him, as the Center, which will bring the Front from the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall aſpect to the right flanke. Now as the body Wheeles, ſo the right Leader muſt obſerue to turne his body by Diſcretion in his place, keeping his aſpect euen with the aſpect of the reſt of the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders as they winde themſelues: and thus your Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions will bee accompliſhed. The ſame thinges to the contrary muſt bee likewiſe obſerued; when you will wheele to the beſt Flancke; If you will bring the aſpect of the Front towards the Reere, then you muſt giue them the halfe turne, by wheeling one quarter turne more then you did before.</p>
                  <p>If you will returne the Body into his place againe, you may wheele it round, by giuing it one halfe turne more, hauing once already had an halfe turne; which will bring that Aſpect backe againe that way from whence it was firſt mooued: But if the Body haue made but a quarter turne to the right hand, then before you wheele them backe, you muſt ſay; To the right hand. And all of them will turne their faces that way: then bid the Leader who was the right hand Leader, and is now become the left, to ſtand firme; And the reſt to wheele backe againe about him the quarter turne: then let them Front as they were, and ſo your firſt Ranke
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20759:29"/>of Leaders hath gotten the place, from whence at firſt it wheeled; Then ſay, Rankes open backward. And when the Rankes haue taken their firſt places and Diſtances, then ſay; Fyles to the left hand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen: ſo all the Fyles turning their Aſpect towards the left flanke, march from the right hand Leader (who hath his place already, and therefore is to ſtand firme) till they haue taken all the firſt places and Diſtances, and then they muſt Front againe as they were: And thus they are reſtored to their firſt Ground and Order.</p>
                  <p>When you intend to wheele a ſingle Company, you muſt Double their Rankes before they wheele, in regard the Body is but ſmall; but in a Diuiſion or greater Body, you cloſe both Ranke and Fyle to the Order of three foot, omitting to Double.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Precepts are to bee vſed to the contrary hand, if you bee wheeled to the left flanke.</p>
                  <p>Now wee will ſay ſomewhat of Exerciſing the Pyke, before we come to the Muſquetier: The pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall handling of the Pyke which euery man is to bee practiſed in, becauſe it is common, wee will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and proceed to the tearmes of Direction; which are theſe: <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Aduance your Pykes.</l>
                     <l>Order your Pykes.</l>
                     <l>Shoulder your Pykes, and ſlope them.</l>
                     <l>Charge your Pykes.</l>
                     <l>Order your Pykes.</l>
                     <l>Trayle your Pykes.</l>
                     <l>Cheeke your Pykes.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:20759:30"/>
                  <head>Theſe following Motions are to bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, both Standing and Marching.</head>
                  <note place="margin">When you Charge and March, your Body muſt ſtand ſtill a while till you ſee your Pykes are all couched ouer their Leaders ſhoulders, then March forwards.</note>
                  <lg>
                     <l>CHarge your Pykes.</l>
                     <l>Shoulder your Pykes.</l>
                     <l>To the right hand Charge.</l>
                     <l>Shoulder your Pykes.</l>
                     <l>To the left hand Charge.</l>
                     <l>Shoulder your Pykes.</l>
                     <l>To the Reere Charge.</l>
                     <l>Shoulder your Pykes. Stand.</l>
                     <l>Order your Pykes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>They muſt obſerue when they Charge ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to fall backe with the right leg, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, to ſet forward the left: When you Charge to the left hand ſtand firme with the right leg, &amp; only turne a litle on your left heele.</p>
                  <p>Now for the Muſquetiers, becauſe ſome Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons there are proper and belonging to them onely For the handling the Muſquet and the Poſtures: wee will omit them, and onely tye you in the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe to theſe three tearmes of Directions, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all the other particularities.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Make ready, Preſent, Giue Fire.</head>
                  <p>Your Muſquetiers muſt obſerue in all their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to turne to the Right hand; and that they carry the mouthes of their Muſquets high, as well when they are Shouldered as in Priming; as alſo when they hold their Pannes guarded, and come vp to giue fire.</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:20759:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>All Skirmiſhes and Fights, are performed one of theſe three wayes: either by Aduancing, or Reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, or by the Flanke.</p>
                  <p>In Aduancing towards an Enemy (if they Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh not disbanded) they giue fire by Ranke, after this manner.</p>
                  <p>Two Rankes muſt alwayes make ready toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and aduance tenne paces before the Body; at which diſtance a Sergeant (or when the body is great) ſome better quallified Officer is to ſtand, euen with whom the Muſquetiers are to come vp, which they are to performe, one Ranke ſtill one after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; the ſecond Ranke obſeruing ſtill to keepe their Muſquets vpon their Reſts, and to guard their Pannes till the firſt haue diſcharged and be fallen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; &amp; then preſently after them, the ſecond Ranke is to giue fire and fall away after the firſt Ranke, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling euen behind the other Rankes in the Reere, and falling vp after them: whileſt the firſt two Rankes come vp and giue Fire, the two next are to make ready, and to aduance forwards as farre as the afore mentioned Officer, and no further, aſſoone as euer the two firſt are falne away; and they are to doe all thinges in the ſame manner they did before them, and ſo all the other Rankes by twoes, one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>When they haue preſented, no man muſt be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to Diſcharge his Muſquet, till the word (Giue Fire) bee giuen, and then the whole Ranke muſt be taught to Diſcharge hanſomely and altogether, no man being permitted to take his ayme higher then the Girdle or the Middle of a man.</p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:20759:31"/>
                  <p>When you will acquaint them to giue Fire, rety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from an Enemy, you muſt do it in this manner:</p>
                  <p>As the Troupe marcheth, the laſt Ranke makes ready; and beeing ready, turneth at an inſtant to the right hand, Preſents and giues Fire; which being performed, they March one after another, a good round pace towards the Front; and there place themſelues together before the Souldiers; as ſoone as the aforeſaid firſt Ranke is turned to Diſcharge, the Ranke next it makes ready; and when the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt is Marched away, the ſecond comes vp after the ſame manner the former did, Preſenting, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Fire, falling away, and performing all thinges in the ſame ſort the former did, ſo ſucceſſiuely the reſt one after another.</p>
                  <p>We giue fire by Flankes, thus; The outmoſt Fyle next you muſt be Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to make ready, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ſtill along with the body till ſuch time as they be ready; &amp; then they are to turne at the Signall gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon the Enemy, &amp; giue Fire altogether at one time: when they haue Diſcharged, they ſtirre not but ſtand firme, keeping their Ground, and Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging their Muſquets againe. Now aſſoone as the foreſaid Fyle turnes to giue Fire, the outmoſt next it muſt make ready, alwayes Marching along with the Body, till the Bringer vp bee paſt a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Leader of the Fyle that gaue fire laſt, and then the ſecond outmoſt Fyle, muſt turne altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and giue fire, doing as the firſt did; and ſo all the reſt of the Fyles ſucceſſiuely one after another. A Sergeant, or if the Troupe bee great, ſome better qualified Officer, ſhall ſtand at the head of the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20759:31"/>firſt fyle, and as ſoone as the ſecond fyle hath giuen fire, he is to lead forwards the firſt fyle, and ſo the reſt one after another, till he hath gathered vp the whole wing of Shotte; and then hee ſhall ioyne them againe in equall front with the Pykes.</p>
                  <p>Another way of skirmiſhing is this; all the whole wing of Musketiers makes ready altogether, and the firſt ranke without aduancing, giues fire in the place it ſtands in, and ſpeedily as it may; yet order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falls away, all the ranks doing the ſame, one after another ſucceſſiuely.</p>
                  <p>Now laſt of all, we will repeate the termes of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, which are theſe:</p>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Motions ſtanding and Marching.</head>
                     <l>Fyles right your Selues.</l>
                     <l>Ranks right your Selues.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Silence.</head>
                     <l>To the right hand:</l>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                     <l>To the left hand,</l>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                     <l>By the right hand to the Reere,</l>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                     <l>By the left hand to the Reere,</l>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                     <l>Rankes to the right hand Double,</l>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                     <l>Ranks to the left hand Double,</l>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                     <l>Middle-men to the right hand Double the Front.</l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:20759:32"/>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                     <l>Middle-men to the Left hand, double the Front.</l>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                     <l>Bringers vp to the Right hand, Double your Front.</l>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                     <l>Bringers vp to the Left hand, Double your Front.</l>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                     <l>Middle-men by Deuiſion, Double your Front to the right hand.</l>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                     <l>Middle-men by Deuiſion, Double the Front to the</l>
                     <l>left hand.</l>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                     <l>Middle-men to the Pyke or to the Sword, Double</l>
                     <l>the Body.</l>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                     <l>Ranks by the Flankes, Double the Body to the right hand. to the left hand.</l>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                     <l>Halfe Ranks by the Flanks, Double the Front.</l>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                     <l>To the right or left hand, Counter-march.</l>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>This is for the Ranks; but when you will Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-march your Flanks or Fyles, you muſt firſt bid them to the right or left hand; vpon which directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they will turne their faces to the flanke you deſire to haue them turned; and then ſay as you did before in the Countermarching the Ranks.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To the right, or to the left hand Counter-march.</l>
                     <l>The ſame alſo is to be loſed in the other Counter-marches, which are theſe; viz.</l>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:20759:32"/>
                     <l>To the right hand Countermarch and ſtand.</l>
                     <l>As you were.</l>
                     <l>Before you wheele the Body, you ſhall vſe theſe words;</l>
                     <l>Fyles, cloſe to your meane order, or to 3. foot.</l>
                     <l>Ranks cloſe to your meane order, or to 3. foot.</l>
                     <l>Aduance your Pykes.</l>
                     <l>Slope your Musquets.</l>
                     <l>To the right hand, Whele.</l>
                     <l>To the left hand, Whele.</l>
                     <l>To the Reere Whele.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>After you haue wheeled to the right hand, to wheele backe againe, muſt be euer to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary hand you wheeled firſt.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Front as you were.</l>
                     <l>Ranks open backward.</l>
                     <l>Fyles open.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>If before the firſt wheeling, they cloſed co the right hand, then they muſt open to the left hand: and ſo the contrary.</p>
                  <p>Front as you were.</p>
                  <trailer>FJNIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
